has the um increase of poppy production
in
Afghanistan uh severely decrease the
price of the Opium that makes its way to
America good question yeah Afghan poppy
has flooded the the heroin market and so
the price of heroin is incredibly low
it's lower in in most cases even than
meth and crack I mean heroin has just
pushed crack out of business because
it's so incredibly cheap now a terrible
side effect of this is as crazy as this
might sound until the late 1970s
Afghanistan was a net food exporter they
actually grew enough food to export to
Iran and to Pakistan and now they have
to import virtually all of their food
they don't produce any rice anymore all
those tomatoes and strawberries
everything that that you see in the
market when you're in Cabo for example
it all comes from Pakistan because
everybody's growing heroin
poppy so did you spend very little time
in Afghanistan most of it was in
Pakistan in the CIA almost all my time
uh in that region was in Pakistan I was
only in Afghanistan for brief
periods
so again did you did you have any um
life lessons or wisdom learned from the
Pakistani experience the people you the
friends you made so to speak the
acquaintances you made yeah and I hate
to say it it's going to sound Grim but
don't trust anybody my closest contact
the guy that I was in touch with day in
and day out the one who had a going away
party for me at his house where his wife
cooked a a dinner and baked a cake he
ended up flipping and joining
Al-Qaeda and um when Al-Qaeda realized
that he was Major khed the guy who was
working with the CIA they beheaded him
and they videotaped his beheading and
now it's for sale in the souk and
paser what's the soup the souk is the
market okay yeah yeah so you know I
guess but you kind of wouldn't you
expect that stuff to happen I mean why
why did you get into the CIA did you
want to be James Bond when you were a
kid I mean did you yeah I kind of did
yeah I I did like you know asking my
parents for walkie-talkies when I was
nine and I would keep logs of what the
neighbor kids were doing yeah I I I
loved the whole the whole idea of being
a spy so you were a little bit of a busy
body then you were watching The
Neighbors yeah I kind of was what were
you worried about were you worried about
uh what they were doing or they're up to
plots I don't even really remember I I
remember I remember accusing one of the
neighbor kids of stealing my dad's
tomatoes so I did surveillance on the
Tomato patch right but yeah all through
my childhood I I wanted to be in the CIA
and then I kind of put it out of my head
and then when I was in graduate school
It's Kind of a Funny Story and this
can't happen anymore because we have the
Equal Employment Opportunity Act which
made this illegal but there really was
an old boy Network you couldn't just
apply to the CIA you had to be spotted
and recruited so I was taking a class at
George Washington University called uh
the psychology of leadership
fascinating class on why foreign leaders
do what they
do as an
example the Yalta Conference everybody
knows the Yalta Conference at the end of
the second world war why was that
Conference held in
Yalta Eisenhower I mean uh uh I'm sorry
Roosevelt had to go all the way around
the war he had to go through North
Africa to Iran and then up to Crimea and
talta it took you know more than 24
hours to do that the man was was dying
he was
sick that's why it was in yala because
Stalin knew he was sick and he wanted to
exhaust him and so when Roosevelt
finally arrived in yala Churchill was
already there and Stalin insisted on the
meetings beginning immediately all
Roosevelt wanted to do was to go to
sleep and so he gave up
Poland just to be able to get to bed
yeah smart guy so I'm taking this class
and the the professor uh gave us an
assignment to Shadow our bosses for a
week and write a psychological profile
on of our bosses I was working uh as an
intern at the time at the United Food
and Commercial Workers Union major labor
union here on K Street in Washington
second largest Union in
America and um I was was a little bit
afraid of my boss he was one of these
oldtime tough guy Union
organizers he had had his back broken
during a riot once and you know scabs
had beaten him and just a tough guy so
we were um halfway through the week it
was
Wednesday and we got into an argument
and I called him a racist which he was
he got so angry he took a stance and he
put up his fists and I remember
recoiling like oh now I've done it and I
I was waiting for the blow to come and
he looks at me and he says my penis is
bigger than
yours and I said what I said I quit
you're nuts and I quit and I walked
out I went back home I wrote my
paper that sounds like The Unofficial
slogan of Washington DC basically it is
yeah this was a learning experience for
me this was I mean hey that's what the
that's the Washington Monument there
yeah that's what they're saying there
you go he was just reading the slogan
he's just speaking it so this was late
1988 early 1989 and uh I I wrote that I
believed I told the story and I said I
believed that he was a sociopath with
Psychopathic and possibly violent
tendencies I get the paper back a week
later and I got an A and the professor
wrote in the margin uh please see me so
I went to see him after class come to my
office I go to his office shuts the door
he says listen I'm not really a
professor here I'm a CIA officer under
cover as a professor here and I'm
looking for people who might fit into
the cia's culture would you like to work
for the
CIA I said why not I was getting married
right after graduation I didn't have a a
job lined up I'd always wanted to work
for the CIA anyway and so
nine months later I'm sitting at my desk
at CIA headquarters so why did they why
did what was the tell was it that you
were interested in sociopaths because I
guess you got to deal with sociopaths
CIA everybody at the CIA is a sociopath
I mean does that mean does that mean you
were too or are or what no I'm glad you
asked that a CIA psychiatrist once told
me that the CIA actively seeks to hire
people who have what they call
sociopathic tendencies not sociopaths
sociopaths have no conscience and so so
they can just wanly violate the law and
not have any remorse but those people
are impossible to control because they
don't respond to polygraphs right if you
have no conscience you don't feel guilty
so you don't
respond with guilt on the polygraph exam
people who have sociopathic
tendencies do have a conscience they do
Express guilt but in the name of the
country and National Security they're
happy to violate the law I can't tell
you how many many houses I've broken
into over the years to plant bugs or
cameras or to steal documents or weapons
or whatever I can't I I've lost count in
Pakistan in 25 different countries but
it's because my country needed me did
you ever run into like a weird dog or a
parrot in the middle of a house no you
you have all that stuff planned out in
advance you can take where where you put
the dog and make him go to sleep and the
parrot you just we never had any
problems with parents I don't I I
remember one bird once but it didn't
what did you do to the bird we just let
go is that classified what you do bir no
we just ignore the bird you never want
those birds to say Jesus Jesus you know
or something like that when whenever
you're walking through right that's
right so did you ever have like a home
alone experience where you actually
walked into a booby trap and like fell
on something and broke the glass or
something close what was it I was I was
in a I was in a friendly
country working with my counterparts
from that country's uh intelligence
service and uh we were I was tasked with
breaking into an apartment so I went
with what's called a locks and picks
officer who's an expert Lo uh lock
picker and this woman whose apartment we
were breaking
into the building it was an eight floor
building and each floor had two
apartments side by side and opposite the
apartments was the elevator we couldn't
take the elevator cuz it made to much
noise so we walked up the flights stairs
went to the sixth floor still
remember and my counterparts had done
surveillance on the building and they
said the targets apartment's on the left
on the right is a married couple he's a
lawyer she's a school teacher they're
both at work I said great so we go up
there and the locks and pick officer is
working on the lock with his little
tools and I'm standing right behind him
him and I hear a voice come from the
next door apartment it turned out the
woman had just had a baby the day before
so she's home she's not at work and the
husband's on paternity leave so he's
there with her too and I hear her say I
think somebody's in the hall and I told
the guy
stop and we're silent and then the
husband says I don't hear anything I
told him go he starts doing it again and
she says no I'm pretty sure I he
something out there I said stop this was
in a foreign language that I happened to
speak so we're waiting the husband says
I think you're imagining things I told
him go he starts going again and then
she says I hear somebody out there and
she comes and opens the door and just as
she opens the door I turn to block him
so she can't see him and she says who
are you and I said oh hello uh I'm sorry
I said I I think I must be lost I'm
looking for from my aunt's apartment and
I gave her a name and she said there's
nobody there's nobody in this building
by that name and I said oh is this
number you know 1205 whatever street and
she says no this is
1207 and I said oh I'm so sorry I must
have the wrong building and she gives me
a funny look but she closes the door and
I told him go and and then we hear click
and the door opens and we went in and
did our thing but we came that close to
getting
caught but you've never had like a booby
trap like a string that's on the ground
that trips you over or somebody knowing
you thank goodness um although in
Afghanistan that happened frequently
Al-Qaeda would booby trap pretty much
everything that they were forced to
evacuate like did they have like Indiana
Jones style traps with like little
spikes come up not nothing arcan like
that a lot of trip wires is what it was
yeah and they would do things like they
would take I have actually some photos
on my phone um they took um Christmas
cards and in the Christmas card they
would put a Detonator so Detonator is
relatively flat right it's like two
quarters on top of each
other or three quarters on top of each
other and then close the Christmas card
so you'd open up the Christmas card it
would blow your hands off oh man yeah so
yeah they they would be trapped a lot of
stuff wow sounds like something alluding
to you put up a Christmas car and blow
your hands off yeah I can't believe that
so um did you ever see any weird animals
in your experiences strange you know
like at
a yeah I must have seen two dozen desert
foxes once in one night in the Sinai
Peninsula I had never seen a desert fox
before and they only come out at night
were you out in the desert yeah what
were you doing camping no camping I'm
going to Camp the lodge star Lodge yeah
Mischief um so where they just came out
in the middle of the night they come out
of their Burrows in the middle of the
night because it's cooler and they hunt
for I don't know mice I guess I don't
know um saw a giraffe once off in the
distance Oh I thought you said someone's
living room maybe some of those people
you have to go after you know they have
they keep wild pets I remember the the
stories of Hol salasi you'd have a whole
train of baboons and lions and
everything scream they they do they
scream yeah that's why have and what did
you see baboons there no no no I'm
saying highly Cass um peacock scream we
saw peacocks a lot yeah both in
Afghanistan and in Pakistan wow yeah
they're very uh they don't like when
people come around them and so they just
start
shrieking so they're good uh like guard
dogs right do you ever had did you ever
have problems with dreams like night
terrors because of the work you did I
left Pakistan 17 years ago and I still
dream about it every single night do you
have a recurring dream yeah I do what is
it it's mostly that Satan's after me and
he's chasing me from H to H really yeah
like a literal Satan yeah like with
horns and spiky tail and everything what
color does it it I mean you see it
visibly in the dream and is it in the
same like a same location a building or
room yeah I'm I'm running around filad
Pakistan like trying to take cover from
Satan I know he's after me I know he's
nearby and I these places are all dumps
and they're all like one room mud Huts
or made out of concrete block and I'm
like I can't hide here Satan's going to
find me for sure so you ever have dreams
of like people you've met or weird it's
just this entity yeah do you believe in
Supernatural stuff or do you just is it
because you're raised in Orthodox Church
yeah I believe in God and the devil
right yeah so that's interesting so you
have this to this day that dream oh yeah
yeah yeah anything any other the
Veterans Administration was developing a
blood pressure medication
um starts with a P but the Name Escapes
Me Now and so they were giv giving it to
patients at the VA hospitals and it
didn't do anything at all to help their
blood pressure but it had an odd side of
a side effect of making them uh forget
what they had dreamt the night before
and so now it's used for
PTSD it's quite effective do you use
that every night you have PTSD oh still
after years from your experience in
Pakistan what was worse now you went to
prison you told me how what was that was
a piece of cake prison was yeah
wow so just the fear of of being you
were like you know in the undercover
state kind of all the time oh yeah so
you'd be a better actor than most people
in Hollywood then really I like to think
I would because your life depended on
you getting the lines right you're like
a method actor like Daniel de Lewis or
something I wish I had Dani Lewis's
money yeah but you could probably
perform better than him in some of those
roles you know maybe I'll tell you I was
very very concerned about my personal
safety in Pakistan very concerned and
one day you know I would I would leave I
I stayed in a small 16 room Guest House
rather than at the Marriott cuz what are
they going to blow up first they're
going to blow up the Marriott and what
did they do four weeks after I got there
they blew up the Marriott and killed 56
people so I stayed in this little guest
house where nobody would know and nobody
would recognize me and um I would leave
every day at a different time and take a
different route to work just for my own
safety one day I leave I'm driving into
the embassy and I see a guy on a
motorcycle wearing a red helmet and he's
trying really hard to stay in my blind
spot now the reason I even paid any
attention to this guy was that he had to
be the only person in Pakistan wearing a
motorcycle helmet I don't even know
where you'd buy a motorcycle helmet in
Pakistan
so I'd slow down he'd slow down I speed
up he speeds up I said oh this isn't
good so I made my way to the Embassy and
when I got to the the entrance to the
Diplomatic quarter he he broke off I
worked a long day 12 13 14 hours so it
was night time by the time I left and
again I took a different route home
every night sure enough there he is he's
on me again well that's the definition
of surveillance it's multiple sightings
at time and distance so I've seen him in
different places at different times and
at different distances from both home
and
work so I'm positive I'm under
surveillance the next morning I woke up
at 5:00 in the morning I went outside I
looked around I didn't see anybody on
the street I took we had these mirrors
on you know sticks and I looked under
the car I don't see any bombs or
anything I get in the car I start
driving around again he's on me 5 o' in
the
morning I get to the Embassy I waited
until the security guy came to work and
I said listen I am under surveillance
I'm 100 % sure and I told him now three
sightings over the course of two days
and he said okay well we have to wait
till the chief comes in so we waited
another hour or two till the Chief came
in went and told him explained
everything gave him all the details and
he said okay he goes you know what you
have to do and I said I know so I signed
out a a 9
millimeter and all day long I I couldn't
focus on work all day long because I'm
thinking I have to kill this guy this
afternoon and I really didn't want to
cuz I had never killed anybody at the
CIA it just wasn't my thing I was always
doing other things right and the guys
were kind of like you know there was
there was seven guys who were working
for me they were come on don't worry
about it don't worry it's all going to
be worth it it's all for your own safety
we're going to have two other cars out
there on you don't worry about anything
midday I went to a joint safe house that
we were running with the Pakistani
intelligence service that's where we
used to interrogate
prisoners and I finished my
interrogation I started walking out and
then I stopped and I turned and I said I
saiden
Muhammad are you following
me and he said no why and I said because
I'm under surveillance I'm positive I'm
under surveillance and if I see this guy
one more time I'm gonna kill him and I
never saw him
again later on a
penetration
of a friendly
service told me that they had been
talking about me amongst themselves and
they said that nobody could be as nice
as I am that has to be fake right that I
was just being that nice to them so that
they would drop their guard because I
must be spying on them and so they put
this guy on me just to see what am I
doing when I'm not with them
well I I wasn't doing anything I was
doing my
work but I was going to kill their guy
because he was a really bad
surveillance did you ever have to kill
anybody no you've never in your life no
thank God not only never killed anybody
no animals never even ran over
squirrel have you dodged a squirrel and
almost lost your life in the process no
I dodged a deer and almost lost my life
in the process did you come eye to eye
with a deer as you're swerving in
training oh wow totally spank a new car
so why don't they fire you then if you
wouldn't take a deer's life how you you
know how many cars we go through oh no
I'm talking about the fact that they saw
that you wouldn't kill a deer that's not
going to be a good agent right now you
know some guys their job is to go out
and kill people and mine wasn't mine was
to recruit people mine was to be the
they saw you as a Salesman as a
cheerleader yeah so you could either let
me take you to dinner and agree to be my
paid agent or that other guy back there
who's not saying anything he's going to
shoot you in the head you have a choice
so you were the nice guy you were the
option A mhm always did you ever
encounter any Good Samaritans that got
you out of a bad spot in your career in
the in the agency no how about the
People You Meet
overseas any Good Samaritans in Pakistan
yeah not in Pakistan but in other places
any story that comes to mind of someone
coming out do going the extra mile or
doing something
that you know what it's still classified
and I probably shouldn't say but yeah
there were some really really
good-hearted people out there
yes what do you think makes a good
Samaritan you know do those kind of
things when they don't have to you know
I asked that question of a
psychologist and he told me that Good
Samaritans whistleblowers people of that
ilk have an unusually clearly defined
sense of right and wrong and it's
because they usually come come from very
tightly
knit um churchgoing synagogue going
whatever families you know this is an
interesting thing about the CIA there is
no ethics training none zero you either
go into the CIA with your own personal
moral code or you don't have a moral
code because it's not going to be taught
to you and so for a lot of people
they're never really sure where that
moral line is that they shouldn't Ross
when I lecture at universities I always
ask the same question as a as an example
of this let's say you're a CIA case
officer and you've recruited a
penetration of a foreign intelligence
service um or no even better of a
foreign terrorist group right so this
guy's the real deal he's given you
information that is allowing you to save
American lives and disrupt attacks and
everything he's told you has been true
so you go to meet with him you're
somewhere in the Middle East somewhere
let's say you're in Cairo or Aman or
whatever and he says to you listen I've
given you everything you've wanted
everything I've told you is true now
you're going to do something for me I
want you to go get me a prostitute and
if you don't get me a prostitute I'm not
going to give you any more information
do you get him the prostitute yes or no
what would you
do